<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="title">The second Boke of the communication of Raphael Hythlodaye, concernyng
            the best state of a common wealthe: conteynyng the discription of Vtopia, with a large
            declaration of the Godly gouernement, and of all the good lawes and orders of the same
            Ilande.</head>
         <div n="1" type="chapter">
            <head type="chapter"><!-- no title --></head>
            <ab>
               <seg n="1.1" type="multisentence">
                  <seg corresp="#es-1-01-1" n="en 1.1" xml:id="en-1-01-1">The Ilande of Vtopia
                     conteyneth in breadthe in the myddell part of it (for there it is brodest) CC
                     miles.</seg>
                  <seg corresp="#es-1-01-1" n="en 1.2" xml:id="en-1-01-2"> Whiche bredthe continueth
                     through the moste parte of the lande, sauyng that by lytle and lytle it commeth
                     in and waxeth narrower towardes both the endes.</seg>
                  <seg corresp="#es-1-01-1" n="en 1.3" xml:id="en-1-01-3"> Whiche fetchynge about a
                     circuite or compasse of vc myles, do fassion the hole Ilande lyke to the newe
                     mone.</seg>
               </seg>
               <seg n="1.2" type="singleSentence">
                  <seg corresp="#es-1-02-1" n="en 1.4" part="I" type="partial" xml:id="en-1-02-1">Betwene thys two corners the sea runneth in, diuydyng them a sonder by the
                     distaunce of xi miles or there aboutes, and there surmounteth into a large and
                     wyde sea, which, by reason that the lande of euery syde compasseth it about,
                     and shiltreth it from the windes,</seg>
               </seg>
               <seg n="1.3" type="singleSentence">
                  <seg corresp="#es-1-03-1" n="en 1.5" part="F" type="partial" xml:id="en-1-03-1">
                     is not rough nor mountith not with great waues, but almost floweth quietlye,
                     not muche vnlike a great standing powle; and maketh almoste al the space within
                     the bellye of the lande in maner of a hauen; and to the great commoditie of the
                     lnhabitauntes receaueth in shyppes towardes euery parte of the lande.</seg>
               </seg>
               <seg n="1.4" type="singleSentence">
                  <seg corresp="#es-1-04-1" n="en 1.6" xml:id="en-1-04-1">The forefrontes or
                     frontiers of the ii corners, what wythe fordys and shelues, and what with
                     rockes, be very ieoperdous and daungerous.</seg>
               </seg>
               <seg n="1.5" type="singleSentence">
                  <seg corresp="#es-1-05-1" n="en 1.7" xml:id="en-1-05-1">In the middel distaunce
                     between them both standeth vp aboue the water a great rocke, which therfore is
                     nothing perillous bicause it is in sight.</seg>
               </seg>
            <!-- the rest of segments of the chapter would follow here -->
            </ab>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="chapter">
            <head type="title">The cities, especially Amaurotum</head>
            <ab>
               <seg n="2.1" type="multisentence">
                  <seg corresp="#es-2-1-1" n="en 2.1" xml:id="en-2-1-1">AS for their Cyties, he that
                     knoweth one of them knoweth them all: they be all so lyke one to an other, as
                     ferfurth as the nature of the place permytteth.</seg>
                  <seg corresp="#es-2-1-1" n="en 2.2" xml:id="en-2-1-2"> I wyll descrybe therfore to
                     yowe one or other of them, for it skylleth not greatly whych; but which rather
                     then Amaurote?</seg>
                  <seg corresp="#es-2-1-1" n="en 2.3" xml:id="en-2-1-3"> Of them all this is the
                     worthiest and of moste dignitie.</seg>
                  <seg corresp="#es-2-1-1" n="en 2.4" xml:id="en-2-1-4"> For the resydwe knowledge
                     it for the head cytie, because there is the councell house.</seg>
                  <seg corresp="#es-2-1-1" n="en 2.5" xml:id="en-2-1-5"> Nor to me any of them al is
                     better beloued, as wherin I lyued fyue hole yeares together.</seg>
               </seg>
               <seg n="2.2" type="multisentence">
                  <seg corresp="#es-2-2-1" n="en 2.6" xml:id="en-2-2-1">The cytie of Amaurote
                     standeth vpon the syde of a low hill, in fashion almoste four square.</seg>
                  <seg corresp="#es-2-2-1" n="en 2.7" xml:id="en-2-2-2"> For the bredeth of it
                     begynneth a litle benethe the toppe of the hyll, and styli contyneweth by the
                     space of twoo miles vntyll it cum to the ryuer of Anyder.</seg>
                  <seg corresp="#es-2-2-1" n="en 2.8" xml:id="en-2-2-3"> The lenghte of it whiche
                     lyeth by the ryuers syde is sumwhat more.</seg>
               </seg>
               <seg n="2.3" type="multisentence">
                  <seg corresp="#es-2-3-1" n="en 2.9" xml:id="en-2-3-1">The ryuere of Anyder rysethe
                     xxiii myles aboue Amaurote owte of a lytle sprynge.</seg>
                  <seg corresp="#es-2-3-1" n="en 2.10" xml:id="en-2-3-2"> But beynge increasede by
                     other small floodes and broukes that runne into yt, and amonge othere ii
                     sumwhat bygge ons, before the cytye yt ys halfe a myle brode, and farther
                     broder.</seg>
                  <seg corresp="#es-2-3-1" n="en 2.11" xml:id="en-2-3-3"> And lx myles beyonde the
                     citye yt falleth into the Ocean sea.</seg>
               </seg>
               <seg n="2.4" type="singleSentence">
                  <seg corresp="#es-2-4-1" n="en 2.12" xml:id="en-2-4-1">By al that space that
                     lyethe betwene the sea and the cytye, and a good sorte of myles also aboue the
                     cytye, the water ebbethe and flowethe vi houres togethere wyth a swyfte
                     tyde.</seg>
               </seg>
               <seg n="2.5" type="singleSentence">
                  <seg corresp="#es-2-5-1" n="en 2.13" xml:id="en-2-5-1">Whan the sea flowethe in
                     for the lenghte of xxx myles, yt fyllethe all the Anyder wyth salte water, and
                     dryuethe backe the fresshe water of the ryuer.</seg>
               </seg>
               <!-- the rest of segments of the chapter would follow here -->
            </ab>
         </div>
         <!-- the rest of chapters would follow here -->
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>